Stanford
University today what we're going to
do oh you had homework right you had
homework to build a black hole and bring
it in
right did you build
one show and tell no
okay all
right I tried that and I of course
by going to Mr gole reported me to w
website which has the calculation
calculation of what um the the radius of
a black hole that had the mass of or had
the temperature of 3°
oh
okay the difference was that they put
bolman's constant in the denominator
doesn't
matter um suppose you didn't know the
answer let try to estimate
it did we do this last time all right we
want a black hole whose temperature is
in 3 de why 3° well 3° is the
temperature of empty
space uh due to the cosmic back
background
radiation so if we had a black hole
which was 3° it would be in equilibrium
with its surroundings now would that be
particularly interesting no because if
it got a little bit hotter by accident
uh you know then it would just proceed
to get yet hotter if it uh got a little
bit cooler by accident by emitting too
many photons it would suddenly get
cooler so there's no real equilibrium
but nevertheless just to just to try out
some numbers a 3° black hole three 3°
Kelvin black hole all right does anybody
know the wavelength of light which is
about 3
degrees if you know it tell me otherwise
I will have to uh uh work it
out it's about a centimeter no it's
bigger it's longer is it near it's not
21 C no no no no no it's not 21
cm it's microwave yeah it's microwave
back microwave
background okay so what so what is it if
it's
a oh no it's not 10
m no no no no no no no no 10 m uh no
no back microwave usually from 1 mm to I
don't know 1 cm but it's certainly on
order of of a it's in the order of
centimet yeah it's in the order of
centimeters so let's just say a
centimeter okay let's say mic what yeah
it's got to fit in a microwave oven
that's right that's right good point so
it's got to be less than a foot
um
H yeah yeah but it's order a centimeter
or so okay now here's a fact if you
haven't noticed it
already um that the
wavelength of
light at the temperature of the black
hole is about the same size as the
radius of the black
hole that's there aren't too many there
aren't too many parameters around that
you can Shuffle around and the radius
the wavelength of light emitted by a
black hole of size r that wavelength is
about R so we can read off from that
what the radius of a black hole which
emits 1 cm light is and the answer is a
centimeter so we now know it's schwar
Shield
radius
now what was the question again how big
was it or how massive massive how
massive okay so let's go with how
massive if it's 1
cm how many cm are there in a a
kilometer 1,00 * 100 100,000 right so
there's 10 to the
5 cm and a kilometer and a solar mass
black hole is about a kilometer big I
don't know maybe it's 2 kilm maybe it's
a little bit bigger but it's a few
kilometers big so
the thing we're thinking about is
100,000 times smaller in radius how
about in Mass
the mass and the radius are proportional
to each other 2 mg so it's 100,000 times
lighter
than the
uh than the
sun about how massive is 100,000 times
lighter than the
sun it's about the Earth it's roughly
order of magnitude the
Earth the mass of the Earth
so if the mass of the Earth were
compressed to a black hole it would
be roughly a
centimeter
so
uh
that's but why uh why did uh why why did
that come up I can't remember now
somebody asked about it or somebody yeah
does that agree with what Wolfram
says um I put the numbers in I got um
about a moon Moon Mass Moon Mass sounds
a little small to
me Moon sounds a little bit small but uh
but the point is it's not a thing that
you're going to hold in your
pocket right okay it's it's pretty heavy
I'm surprised it's Moon Mass I would
have
SP thought lighter but okay let's that's
not
important factor what no no no the the
Moon is about a quarter a quarter of the
radius of the
Earth that doesn't no no no okay let's
let's not get into it let's not get into
it we want to build ourselves a black
hole
now we have some moving parts or some
working parts and let me let me remind
you what the working parts
are the first two working parts are the
Penrose diagrams for flat space and for
a schwart shield black hole so let's
draw them
we don't want to do any real calculation
calculation is too hard we want to draw
pictures and get the basic um
mathematical facts from the
pictures all right so let's start with
flat
space first of all over here just to
remind you what a Penrose diagram looks
like I'll draw a flat space over here
there's
time now the other coordinate in the
problem is not going to be X it's going
to be radial distance so it never goes
negative radius is NE never never
negative radius goes this way I seem to
have made it a little bit negative over
here it goes that way and at every point
at T and R there are also the angular
directions so here are my coordinates my
coordinates are polar coordinates
centered at me I'm right over here I
also have a clock so I'm moving
vertically my clock is uh ticking off
time and and at different distances from
me that corresponds to different R but
at every R there's a sphere of points so
an object could be at any point on that
sphere but we're going to suppress that
sphere we're not going to draw it we're
just going to draw
r&t light rays that move toward the
origin come in along 45° axis light rays
that move out from the origin go out at
45° and so forth all right the Penrose
diagram that goes with this is just
gotten by smushing it smushing is a
mathematical operation um and look it up
in uh Wolfram look Wolfram
smoing all right we smush
it this way and that way until we get it
on a finite
plane and when we do
so and there's more than one way to do
it incidentally but they all look the
same there's more than one functional
form that you can use for the coordinate
Transformations but they all look very
much the same the point over
here that's sort of the origin of both
space and time there's nothing there's
nothing special about this point versus
this point versus this point they're
just a different time but uh let's pick
a origin of time and put it right over
here
this is time equals
infinity and it corresponds to the
location the squished the scrunched
location of
all the people at different
radi who just stand still if they just
stand still they just wind up vertically
up at tals Infinity but on this figure
they
all wind
up
at what looks like a point but of course
that point is not a point it's just the
fact that we've squished
everything smoed
squished these are all
the and they get denser and denser as
you go out here because after all there
is an
infinite distance out to infinity and
that's all being plotted on this Penrose
diagram so the vertical lines which
become kind of
hyperbolas not necessarily exactly
hyperbolas but looking hyperbolic is
they accumulate meaning to say they get
closer and closer over here and here and
that's the vertical lines the horizontal
lines which are the lines of constant
time well the one at T equals zero
that's pretty obvious it starts here and
it goes out to Infinity the one at tal 1
also goes out to
infinity looks like that these are not
necessarily in fact they're not straight
lines as a rule and again they get
closer and closer and closer and closer
as you get up toward the uh infinite
Time same thing in the lower part of the
diagram which I won't
draw right if you've drawn it
correctly then light rays move on
45° lines
as I said that's partly just definition
of the way you draw it and as somebody
pointed out last time had I drawn it
that accurately a light Ray would then
move well apparently I didn't draw it
very accurately because it's going to
wind up over here maybe I can just put
another one
in that's
better and so forth that's a light Ray
from The Origin out a light Ray from out
back to the origin is that way you can
have light rays that started later and
hit the origin later and then go back
out that's fine they're all pretty much
the same except one is later than the
other you can also Imagine light rays
which don't hit the origin so again I'm
the origin you flash your laser at me
and it goes by me at a
meter from the point of view of radial
distance
it comes in from a long distance away
and it sure looks like it's aimed toward
me so it's hard to tell that it isn't
the radial light wave but then as it
gets closer instead of getting into R
equals z it gets a certain minimum
distance in and then goes back out so a
light Ray that misses the
origin is's another one that misses the
origin I'll draw this one bold and bold
comes in pretty much the same and then
goes back out I did draw it with any
great accuracy but you get the
idea they all look the same incidentally
far
away every light Ray uh no matter how
much it misses me by if it's far enough
away it looks like it's aimed toward
me okay that's flat space that's half of
that's one of the moving parts or one of
the Tinker toy elements that we put
together to build our black hole and
when I say build a black hole now I mean
at least mathematically or in
imagination create a black hole as
opposed to just take the mathematical
structure and examine it how would you
go about creating
one uh in the laboratory well we need a
pretty big laboratory but
uh all right the next thing was the
Penrose diagram for the Schwarz Shield
black
hole I drew it for you last time and
I'll redraw it now
it is a little bit odd here's the way
you draw it you begin by drawing a
square but on a diagonal you know a
diamond a square Diamond like that then
you draw another Square Diamond next to
it of the same
size and then from the top of this
diamond you draw a wiggly line to the
top of this diamond and from the bottom
of this diamond you draw a wiggly line
to the bottom of that diamond the wiggly
lines are the singular
ity future
Singularity let's call it Singularity
plus Singularity
minus people outside the black
hole they're over here this side we're
going to find out doesn't really mean
anything so don't don't uh obsess about
this side don't even ask me about it for
the moment we're going to find out what
happens to it here and here are somewhat
unphysical but this region over
here far away from the black hole it
ought to look like flat space if the
black hole were a million miles away and
we're far away from it it ought to look
like good old flat space so it ought to
look like what flat space looks like out
Beyond a certain distance here well
that's not too hard to imagine here's R
equals infinity that matches this point
over
here uh here's tal Infinity here's T =
minus
infinity light rays come in from here
light rays go out
here lines of constant R and that can
mean either schw Shield r or row it
doesn't matter proper distance oh here
is Ral 2 mg right here if you come
in
along a line like that you get to Ral 2
mg right over there let me draw that
line a different
color this is the line t equal
0 and T equals 0 starts far
away and comes in and comes into the
Horizon right at R = 4 M uh sorry 2 mg
so that's Ral 2
mg here's a later time
time here's a later time and so forth
earlier time earlier time now that's
this is Ral 2 mg how about Ral 3
mg in other words farther out from the
Horizon that's going to look something
like
this R equals I don't know 6 mg I'm not
sure exactly where it would be but on
this diagram there's Ral 6 mg R = 100 mg
far from the black hole that's out here
and so forth and so
on so as you can
see this figure and this figure look
pretty similar as long as you're far
away from the black hole but this figure
looks quite different than this one does
near R equals
0 here's r equal 0 light rays bounce off
it there's no R equals 0 that light rays
bounce off here instead a light Ray will
just move right through the
Horizon and hit the
singularity okay so near the black hole
they're different far from the black
hole they're
similar once you're in
here as we've talked about before you
cannot Escape you're doomed you'll hit
the
singularity
okay now the one more ingredient that
goes in is a theorem I called it uh
birkoff's theorem it is called birkoff's
theorem and birkoff's Theorem is a
generalization of Newton's theorem so
let me remind you about Newton's theorem
now we're going to put these elements
together in a
minute Newton's theorem let me first
express it in a general way
if you have a spherically symmetric
distribution of
mass in other words it's isotropic the
same in every direction here it
is it doesn't have to be a
shell it could be a
lump it could be a shell it could be a
solid sphere with uniform density like
the Earth while the Earth is not quite
uniform density or it could be a sphere
like um like Jupiter with varying
density more dense in the center till
you get out to the outer boundary where
it has almost no
density uh it doesn't even have to come
to an end it just uh it's just a
spherically symmetric distribution then
when Newton's theorem
says and the analog uh we'll discuss in
a moment what Newton's theorem says is
if you take any
sphere that the gravitational force of a
test mass of a point at that distance on
that sphere is exactly the same as the
gravitational field of the same amount
of mass not the total amount of mass but
the mass contained within that sphere as
if it were located right at the center
so the force on this particle here is as
if the entire Mass inside the sphere
were concentrated at the center and the
mass outside the sphere has no effect on
the gravitational force on that particle
at
all that's Newton's
theorem okay uh the special case of it
which I'll be interested in oh and yeah
all right
so um what about let's go slowly
supposing the mass distribution
terminates at some radius so that out
beyond that radius there is no
mass then the theorem says that if
you're out beyond that Mass the entire
massive object gravitates as far as
you're concerned exactly as if the
entire Mass were at the
center now let's take the case of a
Shell let's apply that to a
Shell let's apply that to a shell now
the blue line is a shell of
mass the blue
circle or the blue sphere if I want to
be accurate is a
symmetric shell of
Mass uh if we wanted to think really
mathematically uh with too much
Precision no doubt we would imagine it
was an infinitely thin shell but we
don't have to do that all right it has a
certain mass
m and the gravitational field of a
particle on the inside well how do we
find it we take that point we put it on
a
sphere and we say that the gravitational
force on that point is exactly the same
as the gravitational mass of all
gravitational force of all the mass
inside the sphere but there is no Mass
inside the sphere so the gravitational
field or gravitational force on
something inside the sphere is
zero the interior of the sphere is
exactly the same as if there had been no
shell of mass there at all and what
about outside the sphere outside the
sphere it behaves exactly as if the same
amount of mass was concentrated at the
center okay now let's take birkoff's
version of this
theorem b i
r k
FF k h FF burkoff
uh burkoff theum says very similar thing
it says we we'll take the case of a
shell of mass but it doesn't really have
to be a shell shell you can say very
similar things for any Mass distribution
but for the special case of a shell it
says that the metric tensor metric
tensor is the gravitational field or
better yet the geometry the SpaceTime
geometry inside the shell is exactly the
same as if nothing was there in other
words it's just good old flat space time
in Kowski space time the simplest thing
with no curvature no black hole
just empty flat
space and outside the shell of mass m
the metric is exactly the same as if
there were a black
hole near the center here of mass
m so if it's a big shell let's take for
example the mass of the
Earth I'm not going to make a black hole
out of it just take the mass of the
black hole sorry the mass of the Earth
and leave it as the mass of the Earth
the only thing I'm going to do with it
is smooth it out so that it's perfectly
symmetric perfectly symmetric
sphere then it says that if you're
outside the surface of the Earth the
geometry is exactly the same as the
Schwarz Shield metric corresponding to
exactly the same
mass in other words it behaves exactly
the same way or the gra gravitational
field that you would feel the
gravitational field that you would feel
would be the same as that little 1 cm
nugget uh that formed the black hole of
the same mass okay so that's the that's
birkhoff's
theorem now we want to put together we
want to we're going to create ourselves
a black hole and this is the simplest of
all ways to create a black
hole it's simplest of all ways to create
a black hole what you imagine
you try to do this at liore but I don't
think it would work liore you know they
have these lasers that
uh and they shoot them off all
simultaneously and radiation a shell of
radiation comes in and hits something
and squeezes it I have no idea whether
it'll ever work or not I really don't
know to do what they want to do but if
you imagined uh a much more symmetric
field of lasers here where you really
fill this thing up and made it a very
very smooth shell of lasers and then did
your flash thing with the lasers it
would create a shell of light coming in
all right so we would begin then let's
let's undraw the lasers and only draw
draw the sphere of light coming
in so a sphere of
light is coming in with the velocity
C it's propagating in with a velocity C
light has
energy how much energy does this light
wave have whatever it has let's call it
e in fact
from the
outside we would say it has mass eal
mc^2 so whatever the energy of it is
divid it by c^2 and that's the mass of
this object as seen from let's say far
away let's not distinguish energy and
mass E equals
m all right so this object
now is a collapsing shell of mass
collapsing with a speed of light and
berkoff's Theorem or Newton's theorem
berkoff's theorem applies to it what
does it say it says oh incidentally what
I I should have told you when we were
talking about Newton's theorem and
berkoff's Theorem it doesn't matter
whether the mass is moving as long as it
stays spherically symmetric the theorem
is still correct so here the mass is
moving Inward and what we can say is on
the interior of the Shell at any given
time of course what may have been the
interior of the Shell at 1:00 may be the
exterior of the Shell at 2:00 but take
the interior of the Shell at any time
the geometry the metric the
gravitational field is just empty space
as if nothing was there on the outside
what do you have the schwar shield
metric the good old black hole metric so
you're piecing them together we're
imagining taking a region of space with
nothing in it and sewing it together
with a region of space on the outside
and the um the seam the place where
they're sewed together is the mass
distribution let's try to draw a Penrose
diagram for
that let's start with empty flat
space let's begin our drawing with empty
flat space we don't need this
ooh empty flat
space and into that empty flat space
we're going to throw a shell of
light so we begin by drawing empty flat
space here it is over here it's just I'm
going to get rid of some of the lines we
don't need all those lines on it so
here's our empty flat
universe just a
triangle now from far
away we're going to throw in this shell
of light instead of throwing it in from
liore let's throw it in from Infinity so
the light comes in from very very far
away Along a thin
shell and that what does that look like
that looks something like this the red
line here is going to be the trajectory
of the light Ray or the light shell
remember each point in the diagram is
really a two-dimensional
sphere so every point on this diagram
represents a two-dimensional surface and
every point along the light Ray here
really represents a shell of
light so at this point the shell is very
big it's far away and it's moving toward
smaller and smaller R and when it gets
to the center the shell has shrunk to a
point that's a lot of energy that we'
put into a small
volume whatever the energy is if we
squeeze it into a nothing volume we've
created a huge energy density we've
created a lot of energy within a small
volume you might think we make a black
hole okay and and you'll be
right okay let's begin let's take uh the
first half
of berkoff's theorem it says inside the
shell space time is perfectly
flat where is inside the Shell let's
imagine drawing one of
these
surfaces along the surfaces the radius
is increasing where is the inside of the
shell this is not the inside of the
shell that's the outside of the shell
right here's the inside of the shell
from here to here all
right let me draw all the places which
correspond to the interior of the shell
that's all of this all of that is the
interior of the
shell the interior of the shell buroff
tells us is just flat
SpaceTime this diagram here was all flat
space time it means I got the picture
right inside the shell just by drawing
flat space time inside the shell I got
it right outside the shell I don't have
it right what does a burkov theorem tell
me outside the shell says outside the
shell here the metric should be the
metric of the black hole so let's draw
the black hole
metric let's draw the black hole
metric well here it is again but I'm
going to simplify
it now again so we're throwing in a
light Ray from
Infinity it starts out here and it comes
in and boom hits the
singularity
where now is inside the shell and where
is outside the shell inside the shell is
to the lower left outside the shell is
to the upper right so where did I get
the metric right on this
diagram
outside
right out
here that's what it should look like
outside the shell and this that's wrong
also this is wrong so let's erasee
it this part was
wrong burov tells us that's the wrong
thing for here and this part is wrong
notice that among other things I'm
throwing away all this problematic
region with another Universe on the left
a white hole in the singularity in the
past and I'm left with only
this that's the portion of the black
hole metric outside of the
uh of the black hole so here's the light
Ray and it intersects it hits the
singularity right over here here's the
light Ray it comes in and gets the R
equals z right over there these two
points must be the same point the end of
the light rate
trajectory all right if I want now what
I want to do is I want to imagine taking
this and simply paste it on top of
this pasting the two
together and here's what it looks
like out
here that's the the short Shield metric
I've erased the rest of it but here it
is it's
uh everything above this red line that's
what goes here everything below the red
line that's
here that's the simplest black that's
the simplest formation of a black hole
and the reason that I spent some time at
it was to show you among other things
what happens to these crazy regions the
other half of the of the Wormhole Beyond
The Wormhole and what happened to the
white hole white hole is not there the
Wormhole is not there but there is a
singularity there Singularity is there
okay okay having established what any
questions up until
now seems like one of the is the Horizon
and the other well so far we haven't
even talked about the true Horizon of
this geometry yet we're going to do that
in a minute but go ahead ask the
question anyway ask about that point
where they P them together on the upper
left or
maybe y on the on the interior space one
we had an r equal Z but that was right
over here yeah but in the exterior one
we had only the Verizon right no no at
the singularity R is equal to zero right
good that that all right that's a
worthwhile point now if you remember if
you go back to the schwat shield metric
The Singularity was exactly where that
little two sphere shrunk to zero where R
went to
zero okay okay so in fact you're mat
you're matching Ral 0 along here with r
equal 0 along here and they do
match
okay that's the construction of a black
hole that's the way you would do it this
is the kind of black hole you would get
so let let's now ask where is the
Horizon where is the Horizon of this
black hole the definition of the Horizon
now is not Ral 2 mg that was a temporary
definition of the horizon
The
Horizon is the surface which separates
the region all let me let me say this
clearly there are those places where
it's possible to send a message out to
Infinity in other words to send a light
Ray out to
Infinity if you have enough uh fuel in
your engine you have a chance of
escaping from those regions but in
particular light rays can escape from
certain regions and from other regions
they cannot
escape the definition of the Horizon is
the surface which separates those two
regions
period it's the surface in space and
time which separates those two
regions that from which you can escape
the singularity and from that which you
can't well it's very easy to see where
that is you just draw a light cone back
to here
if you're over here can you get
out no you'll wind up at best over
here what about if you're out here can
you get out sure you can send the light
Ray
out anywhere to the lower right of the
green line a light Ray can get out now a
light Ray can also get in you can also
throw a right light Ray in that's just
to say from the outside you can throw
things into the black hole you cannot
from the inside throw things out of the
black hole so the green line here is the
separator that separates the places
where you can escape from those where
you can't escape now notice something
curious below the red line here is just
empty flat
space there was no there was nothing
there it was just good old empty black
space flat
space the signal of the incoming light
shell hadn't even gotten there yet and
yet there is a horizon
there what's going on well just think
about somebody who happens to be over
here he doesn't know anything at all
about this light shell which is going to
come in the light shell he he never he
receives no message that this light
shell is coming in the light shell
originally over here a signal cannot get
to him knows nothing about it the light
shell is coming in but he doesn't know
it has no knowledge of it at all
nevertheless the fact that that light
shell is coming in means he's
trapped he cannot escape to Infinity
that light shell is going to get
him you can see why I don't have to
words uh a picture is work where worth a
thousand words here he's behind this
line he cannot get out of that line
without exceeding the speed of
light and so he's going to hit the
singularity even though there has
nothing has happened there yet the
geometry is flat space and yet the
Horizon is over here the Horizon forms
before the uh the light
shell gets
there does anything really happen there
can anybody see anything somebody moving
over here do they see something
happening no nothing special happens
over there but whether they like it or
not they're doomed by the time they get
past that light show I'll give you an
example I've used the example many times
of a drain hole as a uh as a black hole
the drain
hole a lake a big big lake with a drain
hole in the center where the water is
being sucked out so fast
uh that uh that at some distance away
the the uh drain hole is draining away
water so fast that a rower who is trying
to out Row the current can't out row it
because the velocity inward is too fast
okay so now
imagine that the drain hole is shut off
you've you've um plugged up the drain
hole
you're sitting a couple of meters away
from where the drain hole is nothing is
happening the water isn't moving you're
perfectly
happy uh if it stayed like that forever
you would have no trouble rowing away
but now unbeknownst to you somebody
pulls the plug from underneath and all
of a sudden the water starts rushing
toward the
center you are doomed whether or not you
felt anything going on you're doomed
because all of a sudden uh the velocity
of the water is such that you can't out
row it so there's an example of you've
you're you're past the point of no
return even though there's no flow of
the water at that point same is true
here pulling the plug is analogous to
This Light sheet coming
in once the light sheet uh well the
light sheet comes in anybody who happens
to be in here is
trapped what happens to the Horizon
let's think about the Horizon a little
further here's the Horizon and remember
at each point on this diagram there is a
two-dimensional sphere so each point
along here represents a two-dimensional
sphere what's the size of the sphere
over
here zero all right so we start over
here with a zero size sphere there it
is now we move out a little bit along
the
horizon how big is the Horizon over
here well it's slightly
bigger the Horizon has
grown even though nothing's happened
nothing has been going on in here and
the Horizon keeps growing up until this
point here
when how big is it at this
point 2
mg 2 mg where the mass remember we've
just taken a black hole
geometry and sort of welded it on over
here and the black hole geometry on this
side had a horizon whose size was 2 mg
so it just grows until it becomes of
size 2
mg and then it just stays that way
unless somebody throws in some more
stuff if somebody throws in some more
stuff The Horizon will grow okay so
that's a picture of the uh of the
creation of a black hole from an
incoming light yeah so you're saying the
reason that the the plug gets pulled out
of the drain is because of the sphar is
while getting smaller and smaller
mhm all right but I I only use that
example to show you that even though
nothing has happened yet you could
nevertheless be beyond the point of no
return or you could be like on the on on
the edge of um Niagara Falls at a time
when Niagara Falls was so Frozen up that
it wasn't moving at all and you think
you're perfectly safe there is no point
of no return the water's not moving and
then all of a sudden the ice gives way
and the water starts going you're doomed
it doesn't matter that the that nothing
seemed to be happening same kind of
thing okay shall we take a uh
break regarding the fellow that gets
trapped in in there not knowing what's
coming oh here right here uh and earlier
class we said that all the mass say this
I'm wondering if he if he gets seem to
is he on the outside of the Horizon from
a point of view of a distant Observer
everything that falls on no no the
distant OB Observer can't see him the
distant Observer is out here can't see
him so so does he go right into the
center so what is stat something that's
inside here there he is what can happen
to
him you hit the singularity you can't
avoid it okay so anything that's trapped
into the uh forming Horizon goes to the
singularity uh and stuff that falls in
subsequently appears to be stuck on the
Horizon well okay so he got in here
somehow didn't he I
mean well he was trapped but uh he
didn't begin existence over
here he may have come from here huh it's
it's
particles his
particles maybe he was maybe his mother
was over here and his grandfather was
over here and so forth and so on or
maybe he just accidentally collected uh
came to existence as a funny fluctuation
of a bunch of molecules but those
molecules were there atoms or something
was there the energy was there
beforehand so the energy came in here
and there he is and yes somebody looking
back can see his
grandfather or his father or whoever it
is or his particles but can't see him
in fact what he sees is he sees these
particles just collecting on this
Horizon which is peculiar because in
some sense the black hole hasn't even
formed
yet see look at that this is weird no
this is really weird The Observer up
here looks back and he
sees grandfather falling in and then
there he is he's born over here he looks
back and what does he see he sees
grandfather getting closer and closer
and closer to something which doesn't
exist yet but can't get but never sees
him go past it oh no it goes through
that point very close to the Horizon
intersect at the rest so I mean what
it's a space time diagram it goes
through we're asking what somebody on
the outside
sees we're asking or measures no but
that sight line looking back at where
that Photon has come from it through the
Red Line it goes through the red line
yes so it's it's actually close to where
it
formed the person out here knows that a
black hole
formed he knows a black hole formed he
sees the light coming
from he he has no problem knowing that a
black hole formed he can look back and
he can see the shell coming
in so if person out here knows that the
black hole is formed the odd thing is
that he sees this person over here
getting trapped onto the
Horizon even before the shell got
in looks back looks through the shell
it's just light he can see through light
he looks back through the shell and sees
uh so so that continues the idea that
everything from an outside Observer will
see of any Mass that's in there will be
somehow smushed on to that Horizon right
always right forever and ever and ever
or until the black hole
evaporates
right all right now we're going to come
to the really bizarre questions that
uh have to do with a combination of
black holes gravity and quantum
mechanics and information and all that
kind of thing
um let's draw a picture of the Horizon
now as a different
picture The Horizon is just a
surface
um here it is we're going to fall
downward
now here's the Horizon it's really it's
really a great big sphere but just like
the surface of the Earth is a big sphere
let's take the Flat Earth approximation
or the flat Horizon
approximation and just uh think of the
Horizon being over
here Things fall down in this direction
toward the
Horizon and let's talk about the
properties of the region near the
horizon and what happens to things as
they fall to the Horizon through the
Horizon whatever let's uh let's talk
about what happens to them now one of
the things we discovered earlier on was
that black holes have
temperature black holes have
temperature we even discussed the
temperature I think we even calcul or
roughly calculated
it um they have entropy
the entropy is proportional to the
Horizon area so it's almost as though
the entropy was carried by things which
were sort of wallpapered onto the
Horizon maybe not so surprising since
from outside everything does look
everything that fell in does look like
it's sort of plastered onto the Horizon
so maybe it's not all that uh uh
surprising that the entropy of the black
hole is proportional to the area we
discovered that if we tried to throw in
more bits it made the black hole bigger
every bit increased the area by one
plunk unit the area of the
Horizon and we went through that that's
a Quantum phenomenon involves
har uh
so there was entropy and there was also
temperature anybody remember what the
temperature the Hawking temperature of a
black hole
is let's so let's get rid of some of
these pictures over here and go back
to Hawking temperature of a black
hole let's call it
th you remember what it
was you're going to look in your notes
you're going to
cheat
H bar is it C
cubed I think C
cubed C cubed over 8
Pi
mg which we could also write in terms of
The schwart Shield
Radius 2 mg / c s is the Schwarz Shield
radius so this is also equal I think to
HC over looks to me like
four uh
pi r do I have that
right 2
mg I'm slow I have to put a two here and
then divide by two
yeah yeah but in in particular in units
in which H bar and C are equal to one
which are natural natural units for us
the temperature of the black hole is
proportional to one over the radius of
the
Horizon and the radius of the Horizon of
a big black hole is big and so black
holes are cold they're cold now what
exactly does this temperature mean uh
does can temperature depend on
position in some sense yes and in some
sense no
uh what is a sense in which the
temperature can depend in the position I
can tell you right now the temperature
in New York City is not the same as the
temperature
here okay but you said the temperature
uh can't depend on position right that
somebody says not explain
yourself in empty space it doesn't
matter where you are temper same that's
true in empty space in truly empty space
the temperature is zero in thermal
equilibrium temperature is really only
accurate Ely defined with infinite
Precision in equilibrium temperature is
a thing that has to do with thermal
equilibrium thermal equilibrium is what
happens when everything gets
equilibrated in other words when all the
variations um in
temperature when the heat flows in such
a way as to
increase the entropy to the maximum
amount and then temperature in thermal
equilibrium is exactly constant
now this is a true statement but one has
to understand in a gravitational field
exactly what it
means it does not mean here's a
gravitational
field it does not mean in thermal in
thermal equilibrium it does not mean
that if you took an ordinary standard
thermometer and lowered it down or
raised it up that the temperature would
be the
same uh
uh here's why temperature what does
temperature measure roughly speaking
very roughly speaking it measures the
ktic energy of particles right all right
now supposing we
had uh that the surface of the Earth was
being heated from underneath here's some
Flames these are green Flames heating
the surface of the Earth from underneath
making the surface of the Earth hot and
um it was ejecting thermal molecules
into the atmosphere in fact
those molecules were the
atmosphere let's go to an extreme
situation where the molecules are so
rare that they don't bang into each
other the mean-free path between them is
very large or the molecules are so
weakly
interacting uh that basically what
happens when a molecule gets ejected is
it falls back down so this above the
surface surface of the Earth there are
molecules
they gravitation is pulling them back
down they jump up depending on their
kinetic energy in other words they jump
up by an amount that which depends on
the thermal fluctuations that they might
have gotten hit with the hot surface
here is bombarded vibrating shaking
doing whatever H fluctuating and it'll
kick a molecule up and the molecule will
fall back down okay do you expect the
kinetic energy of the molecules to be
the same no matter how high you
are no why not because they lose kinetic
energy when they rise up right supposing
you wanted you wanted to
know so here's an example where even
though in some very technical sense
which I'm not going to try to describe
for you exactly the temperature is the
same everywhere there is a sense in
which that is true but for our practical
purposes where what we mean by
temperature is that which is measured by
a
thermometer and what is measured by
thermometer the kinetic energy of the
particles that are hitting the
thermometer the temperature would be
higher down low than it would be up
high okay so or the kinetic energy of
the particles would be higher down
low uh the same would be true
incidentally if these were not mole
molecules but we were radiating
photons photons would also get radiated
and photons are also subject to
gravitational
forces photons which are radiated will
also fall back down in fact as they rise
they lose energy as they fall they gain
energy so it's the same with photons
photons are no different all right now
let's
suppose
you were very very far away you didn't
want to get too close to this thing but
you wanted to know what the temperature
was down below what Would You Do Well
you measure the temperature high up and
you say well it's half a degree
temperature high up here but you could
extrapolate down and say if the if the
typical kinetic energy of a particle or
a photon that you see up 100 miles from
the surface is such and such
then you could just use some
straightforward extrapolation and figure
out what the uh where the temperature is
down near the horizon or horizon or near
the uh near the surface of the Earth in
this
case now what is the Hawking temperature
the Hawking temperature is the
temperature seen by a
thermometer far from the black hole it's
the actual temperature that a
thermometer would register if it that
were very far from the black hole it
would be registering the presence of
photons thermal photons black body
thermal
photons which somehow were rejected from
the black hole and which were out there
as a kind of atmosphere far from the
black hole which were exciting the
thermometer far away and the temperature
is pretty
cold but in the same way you can
extrapolate
downward and ask what the temperature
must have been close to the surface of
the black
hole there actually is a formula for
doing
it uh it's I think it's a little bit too
late now maybe we can go through it
another time how you actually calculate
the variation of the actual measured
temperature in a gravitational
field but I'm going to tell you the
answer the answer first of all is that
very far away the temperature is the
Hawking temperature where is it there it
is right over here as you get closer and
closer to the black hole the temperature
rises and as you get very close to the
black hole as you get close to the
Horizon we won't call this the Hawking
temperature it's kind of the
extrapolated Hawking temperature what
you would extrapolate into let's give it
a name t of row
it's the temperature measured at a
proper distance Row from The Horizon it
is 1 over 2 pi
Row 1 / by 2 pi Row the closer you are
the higher the
temperature now in
fact the
Horizon is a very difficult place to
escape from in fact if you're behind the
Horizon you can't escape at all if
you're right at the horizon or very
close to the Horizon it's extremely
difficult to get away which is another
way of saying you lose a lot of energy a
photon loses a lot of energy when it
tries to escape from very close to the
Horizon so if you see a finite
temperature a distance above the Horizon
then extremely close to the Horizon the
kinetic energy must have been very long
large that's what's going on here the
actual temperature of the photons or of
a thermometer that would be lowered on a
cable here's our experiment we're going
to lower
thermometer on a cable going to be a
tiny tiny thermometer because for one
reason or another we have to use tiny
thermometers but we'll lower a tiny
thermometer on a cable the cable will
send back a signal telling us what the
temperature recorded on the thermometer
is and as you lower it down you'll find
the the the temperature goes up up and
up and up and
up
uh well if you really believed
this then you would say that the
temperature close to the Horizon was
very very hot now we have a funny
situation now
um let's suppose we take an atom and we
lower it down closer and closer to the
Horizon what happens to that atom as it
gets close to the
Horizon
time what forget forget general
relativity now it's just moving into a
very hot
region what happens to
it becomes
excited but uh it's getting hot it's
getting really really hot
it gets
ionized it's getting really really
hot the nucleus gets uh Torn to Pieces
by the high temperature the quarks get
liberated defeated H it's defeated it's
defeated yeah yeah right well
yeah
right yeah that's right I mean you know
right if we lowered uh if we put a cable
around you and lowered you down and put
your feet to the surface of the black
hole you would get a hot for right right
that's what this picture says and how do
you get away from it you've done a
calculation you've done a legitimate
calculation and this is a legitimate
calculation I mean the calculation is
correct that uh and uh by now it's been
tested over and over again if you do
lower something down on a
cable and uh
then pull it back up it will give all of
the evidence of having been in a very
very hot
region so this uh this is this is not to
be questioned but um there's something a
little funny about this because from
this point of view and from this picture
over here the Horizon is nothing very
special it's just a green line that I
drew there but there was nothing
there
it was just a mathematical line that I
drew to separate the region from which
you can send the signal out to a s where
you can't send the signal out but on the
other hand nothing special was going on
in this Horizon over here the curvature
didn't get large the metric near the
Horizon was close to Flat space we've
already established that and so there's
nothing very dramatic going on and so
you might expect that if you dropped
something through the horizon
and now think about it in the frame of
reference of the falling object the
falling object doesn't say it took an
infinite amount of time to go
through here's the falling object going
through the
Horizon the clock ticks off seconds it
took exactly 7 Seconds to go from here
to here in the frame of reference of the
falling object the object says I fell
through well I fell past the point where
I originally calculated there was a
horizon he doesn't say bump I just felt
the
Horizon but when he was outside the
black hole he made a calculation of
where the Horizon was estimated how long
it would take him to fall through it
fell through it nothing happened okay so
from the point of view of somebody who
falls through the
Horizon nothing happens at that point it
sounds contradictory it sounds I mean
either either he does get burned up or
he doesn't get burned up and if he
doesn't get burned up how did he avoid
the consequences of this very very high
temperature or it could be an atom does
the atom get ionized and if it does get
ionized though its particles get spread
over the entire Horizon by the extremely
high high heat which causes things to
diffuse or does it fall through here
there got to be an answer it's one or
the other it can't be both right
um
so I think one way of trying to get at
this is to think to try to think as much
as possible in what I would call a um an
einsteinian kind of way or maybe it's a
Heisenberg kind of way to try to be to
to try to be operational about it to try
to say
look let's see if we can prove or
disprove this or that by doing an
experiment now here's the kind of
experiment that you might try to think
about the temperature of this atom here
increases as it falls down in fact it
gets very hot before it passes through
the Horizon it doesn't have to go
through the Horizon to get good and
hot how hot does it have to get to ion a
hydrogen
atom 13 13 electron volts right how high
how hot is that that's a 300 3,000
degrees something like that yeah few
thousand degrees so at some point it
reaches 3,000 de it's outside the
Horizon at that point if all makes
sense then it should get
ionized and that's before it fell
through therefore it ought to be able to
send the signal back out or somebody
stationed over here ought to be able to
send the signal back out and said the
adom either did or didn't get
ionized from one point of view the the
atam ought to be able to say nothing's
happening to me I'm falling freely
through the Horizon I'm within uh I'm
within a certain distance of the Horizon
you told me the temperature was going to
be 3,000 de but I don't feel a darn
thing and I'm going to send out the
message to you and tell you right from
the other point of view you've done a
mathematical calculation which says that
the temperature gets hot you've got a
conflict a real conflict so let's see if
we can turn it into an experimental
conflict uh in fact before we do I want
to remind you of uh the Heisenberg
uncertainty
principle and the reason is the
logic that goes on here and that is
important in
understanding this better is very close
to the the logic of uh that Heisenberg
used what Heisenberg say he said you
can't measure both the position and
velocity of a particle okay uh in fact
in some sense it can't have both a
position and a velocity has one or the
other or you can measure one or the
other uh if um having a certain property
means that that property can be measured
then it has one or the other and not
both and that seems contradictory why
does it seem
contradictory if it makes sense to talk
about the position of a particle at any
time then it makes sense to talk about
the sequence of positions of the
particle if it makes sense to talk about
particle then it has a trajectory and
that trajectory can be used to uh to
extrapolate and find the velocity for
the particle so so if it's really true
that that the particle has a position at
every
instant then how can it not have a
velocity at every instant all right so
Heisenberg said all right I don't care
what you say about whether it does or
doesn't let's ask if we can really
measure both simultaneously and I'll
just this is I just want to very quickly
remind you of the logic here so
supposing you uh you have a particle an
electron and you want to measure its
position to high precision
you want to measure its position to high
Precision how do you do it you hit it
with a photon you create an image of it
on a screen and in order to have the
resolving power to see the location of
that electron to within a resolution
Delta X you have to have a photon you
have to hit it with a photon or a light
wave
whose
wavelength is no
larger is less than or equal to Delta X
but then if the wavelength is less than
Delta X that says that the momentum is
larger of the photon is going to be
larger or equal the plunk constant over
Delta
X is that the plun constant with the
cross or without the cross it doesn't
matter okay that means means that this
particle is going to get bombarded by a
photon in order to measure it you might
have said look I believe that particle
is standing still I've created that
particle in such a way that it's
standing absolutely
still and I want to confirm that it's
standing I want to confirm that it's
standing absolutely still at the origin
so what I will do is measure its
position very quickly and then
instantaneously afterwards measure its
velocity and try to check that it was
both at the origin and at rest well you
know the story I mean the story is
extremely well known I I I just I'm just
reminding you of it that if you have to
hit it with a particle of momentum
P it's going to get hit it's going to
recoil the particle is going to go off
in some Direction with a momentum more
or less of order p in what direction
well that direction is somewhat
random uh and so if you try to measure
the velocity
afterwards it will not be what you
thought it was in the first place in
other words the experiment creates
exactly the condition that it was
designed to show wasn't the case the
experiment was designed to
show that the velocity was Zero let us
say and just the experiment itself
created the condition
which was the opposite of what it was
designed to
confirm that's the Heisenberg logic it's
deeply of course connected with quantum
mechanics har appears in it um In
classical electrodynamics you can make
an image with an arbitrarily small
amount of uh arbitrarily low intensity
electromagnetic
wave you don't have to have one whole
Quantum in in quantum mechanics you
can't subdivide the energy less than a
Quantum so if you want to do the
experiment you're stuck you're going to
you're going to give that electron a
kick okay let's uh let's now analyze
let's be Heisenberg and analyze the
question what happens when an atom Falls
onto the Horizon does it or does it not
get um ionized
does it does it not get really mutilated
by the high
temperatures above a certain line here
sorry below a certain line below a
certain line here's the line
row at a distance row where the
temperature T is 1 over 2 pi
row now what we're interested in is when
the atom Falls below the line where the
temperature has exceeded the ionization
temperature we're not interested in what
happens when the atom is above the
region where it's nice and cold we're
interested in what happens to the atom
when it gets within uh within the region
where the temperature is of order the
ionization
temperature once it gets down that low
it's in this huge gravitational field it
fell from above
the huge gravitational field near the
black hole has accelerated it and it's
accelerated it by that point up to close
to speed of light in uh in just because
just because the gravitational field is
so intense near the Horizon so hard to
get away big gravitational field this
thing is falling downward now with close
to the speed of light how much
time does it have before it actually
falls through the horizon once it's
through the Horizon it you cannot find
anything out about it once it's through
the Horizon all right so how much time
does it have the fall that distance well
the answer is what is it row over C if
this distance is
Row the time that it has is row over
C which is um proportional to
proportional to one over the temperature
one over the ionization temperature the
higher the ionization temperature the
shorter the amount of time that the
particle has in that
region okay now how are we going to do
an experiment from the outside to
determine whether the uh before it falls
through it's too late once it falls
through the Horizon too late can't get
any information out we want to find out
during this period a short period of
time here while it's falling in the high
temperature region we want to try to
find out if it uh if it was ionized how
do we find out if it's ionized well we
shine some light on it here might be a
source of light over here that light is
going to illuminate it bounce
off and create an image this image over
here is either going to be an atom un
ionized or it's going to be an atom
splattered all over the place one or the
other we don't know which okay we have a
very short amount of time to do the
experiment namely the amount amount of
time that it takes to fall from the
region where the temperature first got
hot enough to ionize it till it falls
through the Horizon that's a short
amount of time that means what does it
mean in terms of um of resolution
power another way to say it is we have a
small distance that we have to resolve
we have to see that atom within a small
distance that small distance is row what
does it
mean well it means that that photon had
had had better have a wavelength which
is smaller than the distance
row so
Lambda has to be smaller than row and
that says that the energy of that Photon
has to be
larger I'm going to let's see H
bar over Lambda time C / c
um let's see e is p * C this is
p
c right or H H actually have a
row the energy has to be larger than
this the smaller the wavelength the
larger the energy and Lambda is of order
row so the energy has to be larger than
this okay well this is essentially
exactly the
energy that corresponds to this
temperature one over row we didn't put
in the H bars and C's here one over row
one over row same thing here in other
words you have to hit the particle you
have to hit the atom with a photon which
is energetic enough to ionize it in
order to see it in that period you have
to hit it with a photon which is
energetic enough to ionize it in other
words you have to create exactly the
conditions which the experiment was
designed to show do not
happen the experiment will ionize the uh
uh the uh the atom and there is no way
to check whether it was the experiment
that ionized the atom you try to do it
you try to do it again after the
experiment and see if it's still ionized
yes it'll be still ionized any
experiment that you do which is designed
to prove that the atom wasn't ionized
will ionize the
atom and ionize the atom in an
uncontrolled way in a way that you that
uh that you can't go back and uh check
that the atom was not ionized so yeah
wouldn't that high energy ionize it even
in the frame of the falling
object get hot yes in the frame of the
falling
object yes it's just yes that that that
atom gets whacked that atom doesn't like
what happen happened and if somebody out
here were to monitor you and see whether
you can fall through the horizon or not
if they didn't an experiment to check
they would evaporate
you but if I'm just falling through but
if you're falling through and nobody
does the experiment you're fine falling
through and somebody does do an
experiment then you then you're in
trouble and you're in trouble don't do
that couldn't you measure far away from
the Black
and look for gradients and from
that no you'd have exactly the same
problem if you try if you try to check
that the temperature is R
Rising uh what are you going to check
what are you going to check about it
let's say you just drop a thermometer
down you drop a thermometer let the
thermometer freely
fall and you want to find out if the
thermometer has gone up a little bit how
do you find find out you can't ask the
thermometer the thermometer is falling
down you've got to get some radiation
back from the thermometer so you have to
hit it with some
radiation in order to you have to look
at it you have to look at the
thermometer have record while it's going
down well something has to interact with
the
thermometer and what you'll always find
inevitably you pull it back back up
after it has recorded its descent oh
then it will show that it was
hot then it will show that it was hot
just the acceleration of turning it
around will make it hot no but it it
reports the time so During the freeall
period only look at that per as long as
you can be getting information back that
information will be coming back in the
form of quanta and those Quant will
either have been emitted by the object
or have been interacted with the object
there's no way you can get information
without getting quanta back from the
object either the object radiated those
quanta and therefore recoiled or you hit
it with Quant there just no way to do it
without uh without influencing the
object and the amount of influence is
always always
exactly what uh what the temperature at
that point would have done so it's a
it's a sort of Catch 22 you canot do the
experiment without causing the thing you
were trying to show to yes
Kevin so the high energy of a photon
there is to resolve a small distance
yeah is is that or or a small time does
that end up being the same thing as
saying that to get that to get that
reflected observation back out of the
black hole takes a tremendous amount of
energy because you're getting
it strictly you're not trying to get it
out of the black hole it hasn't fallen
into the black hole yet yes out of the
region near the Horizon takes a huge
amount of energy to get does that really
end up being the same yeah yeah yeah it
does it does in the end of the day it
does
uh
right
yeah that Photon did not have to be a
high energy Photon by the time it got
out because in traveling out it will
lose some energy but it did have to be a
high energy Photon in the region in here
and this atom doesn't care what the
photon energy was out here it wants to
know what the energy that was uh what it
was hit with way if it's going to admit
the the the measurement or the
information itself it has to admit it
it's such a high energy absolutely that
region right yeah it doesn't have to be
an external Photon hitting it it could
be something that it naturally emitted
but uh that's
right it seems the at falling into the
black hole have a preferred Direction
namely The Horizon and typically we
don't call a temperature directed chical
chical energy you throw a baseball call
it hot you just say it has kinetic
energy
right well it's not the it's not the
kinetic energy of the object which is
falling in the object is falling in its
kinetic energy is in temperature but
it's interacting with an environment
which is getting hotter and
hotter it's the environment that it's
interacting with which is uh which is
very hot the radiation from the black
hole it's the radiation from the black
hole check with the a magnetic field is
the I is the I what's
that can you check the magnetic
field
uh if you you
look you could do an experiment you
could imagine an an experiment in a
laboratory that's falling with the
atom could be magnetic fields whatever
is in that and that experiment as you
fall into the atom could be doing the
experiment the problem is getting the
information back out of the black hole
right so whatever happens in that
laboratory you have to uh you have to
interact with a laboratory with
something external and then get the
information back out and it will always
be the case that the um that the energy
of the photons that are necessary to get
that energy that information back out
are the same or at least as big as the
energy of the environmental photons in
the thermal
bath so so so if I have a
transmitter in the thermometer by the
time I get close to the event Riz that
temperature the amount of energy I have
to generate to send the signal out with
evaporate anyway exactly isn't that
distance really very small very small
very small no that's that's the point
you don't you're the the distance over
which the temperature is high is very
small all right so you can either think
that you have to have a photon of high
spatial resolution or High Time
resolution either way you'll either say
the photon has a high momentum or it has
a high energy and yes this is all
equivalent to the usual Heisenberg uncer
Principle for time and energy right well
that's what we've used yes yes yes yes
so this this puzzle about what goes on
at the at the surface of a black hole
whether it does or doesn't get hot gets
all mixed up with these questions of um
of uh Quantum uncertainties and so forth
and that's the result there's no way to
answer the question other than to do the
experiment and when you do the
experiment the experiment will do
exactly what you were trying to show
didn't
happen that's a
yeah okay have high enough resolution to
catch it in that window um is it
possible to use a lower resolution lower
energy and do it a bunch of times and
hopefully it just catch it right you
only get one shot at each particle
falling through the Horizon is the
probability just too ridiculous to even
you say supposing I did the same
experiment over and over with many many
atoms and use a low
resolution um I don't know I never
thought about that one uh
they try to use less less energetic
photons of course each one it's a good
question it's a it's a sensible question
ought to be answered you
know we have have to have enough energy
to get something to come out right same
problem you have with right but you
don't have to do you have to have enough
energy pick it
out there's not going be any
loopholes to uncertain principes
yeah
right right you can't beat the
uncertainty principle uh by
uh by what you're trying to
do are we saying we can we can predict
that the person falling in won't feel
the temperature no we can only say
that the experiment
will in
itself cause the conditions that I was
trying to prove didn't happen that's all
we can do from this kind of
analysis in other words what we if
somebody comes and says
look I'm
convinced that uh
that somebody who falls through the
Horizon nothing happens to
them then my answer will be yes can you
do an experiment that shows that and the
answer will be no you cannot do an
experiment that shows that that's all
this is designed to show that uh that at
a level of
operational experimental physics it
would be impossible to
confirm that the uh that uh that the
atom did not experience a high
temperature and we'll come back we'll
we'll look at a couple of more gonan
experiments and try to see what they say
um of course there's no way to say what
happens if no experiment is
done you know it's very much like the
two slit experiment where if you don't
do an experiment there's no meaning to
the question of which slit you went
through uh so if you don't do an
experiment there's no answer to the
question yeah right okay let's uh let's
call it a night and I'll see you next
week for more please visit us at
stanford.edu